A Guide to the Papers of Edgar Finley Shannon 1837-1996
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Edward Finley Shannon 1837-1996
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12706
This addition to the papers of Edgar Finley Shannon (1918-1997), the fourth president of the University of Virginia, from 1959-1974, and Commonwealth Professor of English, from 1974 until his retirement in 1988, consists of 5,000 items (19 boxes, ca. 8.5 linear feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library by Eleanor Salem Shannon, Hanover, New Hampshire on November 20, 1999.
Biographical/Historical Information
Edgar F. Shannon, Jr. (1918-1997) was born to Edgar F. Shannon, Sr. and Eleanor Duncan Shannon on June 4, 1918 in Lexington, Virginia, where his father taught English at Washington and Lee University. Shannon also attended Washington and Lee University, graduating summa cum laude. He also received a Master's degree from Duke University in 1941 and from Harvard University in 1947, following his World War II military service in the United States Navy as a junior gunnery officer on the U.S.S. Quincy until it was sunk on August 8, 1942. Shannon remained at sea on active combat duty until V-J Day, participating in most of the major Pacific campaigns. He earned a Bronze Star and ten other battle stars during his service. He studied at Merton College, Oxford University, from 1947-1950 as a Rhodes Scholar, receiving his doctorate in philosophy in 1949.
In 1946, Shannon taught naval science and tactics at Harvard, and English from 1950-1956, becoming known as a scholar in Victorian literature. While on leave to England in 1953-1954, studying on Fulbright and Guggenheim research fellowships, Shannon began to concentrate on his life-long interest in the literary career and letters of Alfred Lord Tennyson. He wrote Tennyson and the Reviewers, 1827- 1851 and with Professor Cecil Y. Lang, co-authored a three-volume work, The Letters of Alfred Lord Tennyson. Shannon joined the University of Virginia faculty in 1956 as an associate professor of English.
Edgar Shannon served as the President of the University of Virginia from 1959-1974, still teaching part-time, and returned to full-time teaching in 1974 as the Commonwealth Professor of English. His presidency saw an increase in enrollment at the University, efforts to attract a first-rate faculty, racial integration, improvement in the facilities of the University, the achievement of full coeducation, and the social unrest caused by the Vietnam War and other issues.
Among the honors and positions he held were the Thomas Jefferson Award (1965), the Jackson Davis Award (1975), the Algernon Sydney Sullivan Award (1939, as a student, and then a second time in 1975), a member of the Rockefeller Commission to investigate the domestic activities of the Central Intelligence Agency (1975), the boards of Washington and Lee University, the White Burkett Miller Center for Public Affairs at the University of Virginia, the U.S. Naval Academy at Annapolis, the U.S. Air Force Academy at Colorado Springs, the Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation, and the Colonial Williamsburg Foundation. Shannon also served as an elder at the Westminster Presbyterian Church of Charlottesville, and was a member of the Raven Society, and the Author's Club (London).
Edgar Shannon married Eleanor Bosworth of Memphis, Tennessee in 1956 and they had five daughters. Eleanor Bosworth Shannon was an assistant professor of history at Rhodes College, Memphis, Tennessee, from 1949- 1955, the acting dean of women from 1952-1955, and a trustee from 1980-1984. She graduated magna cum laude in international relations from Sweet Briar College and was a member of Phi Beta Kappa. She studied at Balliol College, Oxford, before earning her master's degree in history from Cornell University. Eleanor Shannon won the Algernon Sydney Sullivan Award in 1972 in recognition of excellence of character and service to humanity. She also served as an elder at Westminster Presbyterian Church. In 1990, both of the Shannons established the Foundation for Excellence in Public Education: Charlottesville/Albemarle to provide resources for public school teachers, which was renamed in 1997 as The Edgar and Eleanor Shannon Foundation for Excellence in Public Education: Charlottesville/Albemarle. She died in Charlottesville, Virginia, on March 3, 2000.
Scope and Content
This addition to the papers of Edgar Finley Shannon (1918-1997), the fourth president of the University of Virginia, from 1959-1974, and Commonwealth Professor of English, from 1974 until his retirement in 1988, consists of 5,000 items (19 boxes, ca. 8.5 linear feet) including family correspondence, research and correspondence on family genealogy and history, scrapbooks and photograph albums, news clippings, obituaries and memorial programs, photographs, social calendars and guest books, and memorabilia.
Topics of interest in the correspondence of Edgar F. Shannon, Jr. series includes the period of student unrest at the University of Virginia culminating in the student strike in 1970 or the "Seven Days in May" (see correspondence and news clippings in Boxes 2, 8, and 9), particularly an exchange with Governor Linwood Holton over the Vietnam War controversy (October 2, 1970, Box 2). Other topics include correspondence about Shannon's selection as President of the University of Virginia and his retirement in 1974. There are also letters from his parents and grandparents to Shannon as a boy and young man, correspondence about the Vietnam War controversy and correspondence voicing concern about the proposal to admit women to Washington and Lee University.
The second series contains much personal family correspondence of Susan Lee Duncan, Edgar F. Shannon, Sr., and Eleanor Duncan Shannon.
The third series consists of topical files, including: family papers and genealogy of the Shannon, Duncan, and related families, including Eleanor Duncan Shannon's research on the Duncan family, correspondence, handwritten notes, and copies of records; the Commission on CIA Activities within the United States (Rockefeller Commission); Colonial Williamsburg Foundation; the Life Executive Space Tour; many news clippings concerning the career of Edgar Shannon and the University of Virginia; miscellaneous photographs about the Shannons; school papers of Edgar Shannon, Jr. as a student; travel to Great Britain, Germany, Japan, Sweden, and Norway; Shannon's service in the United States Navy; and the controversy about coeducation at Washington and Lee University. The third series also includes speeches by Shannon (Boxes 10 and 13).
The fourth series contains various memorabilia, bound volumes, scrapbooks, photograph albums, an address book, calendars and guest books kept by Eleanor B. Shannon at Carr's Hill, and a diary of Eleanor Duncan Shannon.
The fifth series contains restricted items removed from public access because of the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act.
Arrangement
The papers of Edgar F. Shannon have five series: Series I: Correspondence of Edgar F. Shannon, Jr. (Boxes 1-2); Series II: Correspondence of other members of the Shannon family (Boxes 2-4); Series III: Topical Files (Boxes 4-13); Series IV: Scrapbooks, Photograph Albums, Other Bound Volumes, and Memorabilia (Boxes 14-18) and Series V: Restricted Materials (Box 19).
Separated Material
The following oversize and audiovisual items are not boxed with the collection but are housed separately under the numbers following each item:
Prologue to an Inauguration: Audiotape 0203, 0204 [might duplicate T422, T423]; Phonograph records (12 in): Phonodisk 0723, 0723-a, 0723-b, 0724; "Edgar Shannon Archive": Disk 0302; Dumas Malone award: Audiocassette 0577; Unidentified Audiocassette: 0578
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence of Edgar F. Shannon, Jr. (Box 1-2)
  - Correspondence 1957-1997 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Correspondence - concerning Virginius Dabney's account of Edgar Shannon and the University in May 1970 1980-1981 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Correspondence - Emma article 1956-1957 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Correspondence - Greeting Cards 1918-1957 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Correspondence - Invitations 1904-1942 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Correspondence - Miscellaneous fragments, envelopes, etc. 1887-1957 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Correspondence - Postcards (all are blank) ca. 1970 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Correspondence - President of the University, Election of 1958 Jul. 24 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Correspondence - Edgar F. Shannon's retirement as President of the University 1973 Jan.-Feb. 9 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Correspondence - Edgar F. Shannon's retirement as President of the University 1973 Feb. 12-Dec. (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Correspondence - Edgar F. Shannon's retirement as President of the University 1974 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Correspondence - Edgar F. Shannon and family [1922 - 1941] (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Correspondence - Edgar F. Shannon and his parents [1934 - 1957] (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Correspondence - Vietnam War Controversy (Seven Days in May) 1968-1970 May (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Correspondence - Vietnam War Controversy (Seven Days in May) 1970 May 13-1976 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Correspondence - Washington and Lee University coeducation 1984 (Box-folder 2:3)
- Series II: Correspondence of other members of the Shannon Family (Box 2-4)
  - Correspondence - Susan Lee Duncan (grandmother) 1857-1895 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Correspondence - Edgar F. Shannon, Sr. (father) 1904-1937 (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Correspondence - Edgar F. Shannon, Sr. (father) 1904-1905, 1910 (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Correspondence - Edgar F. Shannon, Sr. (father) 1915-1916 (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Correspondence - Edgar F. Shannon, Sr. (father) 1919, 1921 (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Correspondence - Edgar F. Shannon, Sr. (father) 1922 Sep. (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Correspondence - Edgar F. Shannon, Sr. (father) 1922 Oct.-Nov. (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Correspondence - Edgar F. Shannon, Sr. (father) 1923 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Correspondence - Edgar F. Shannon, Sr. (father) 1930-1931, 1935 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Correspondence - Edgar F. Shannon, Sr. (father) n.d (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Correspondence - Eleanor D. Shannon (mother) 1910 (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Correspondence - Eleanor D. Shannon (mother) 1916 (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Correspondence - Eleanor D. Shannon (mother) 1922 (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Correspondence - Eleanor D. Shannon (mother) 1922 Nov.-1923 (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Correspondence of Eleanor D. Shannon (mother) 1892-1939 (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Correspondence of Eleanor D. Shannon (mother) 1940-1957, n.d. (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Correspondence - Eleanor D. Shannon (mother) and Eleanor Bosworth Shannon (wife) 1956-1957 (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Correspondence - Eleanor D. Shannon (mother) and the Daughters of the Confederacy 1907, 1921 (Box-folder 4:4)
- Series III: Topical Files (Box 4-13)
  - Bicentennial 1976 (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Biographical information 1992, n.d. (Box-folder 4:6)
    Memorial Service Programs and Tributes for Edgar F. Shannon, Jr. and Eleanor Bosworth Shannon
  - Bosworth, Eleanor "The Abraham Narrative: a term paper" 1955 (Box-folder 4:7)
  - Bosworth, Eleanor "Anthology" 1938 (Box-folder 4:8)
  - Brochures 1923-1943 (Box-folder 4:9)
  - Calendar - Social events at Carr's Hill, arranged chronologically 1959-1970 (Box-folder 4:10)
  - Calendar - Social events at Carr's Hill, arranged chronologically 1970-1974 (Box-folder 4:11)
  - Calendar - Social events at Carr's Hill, arranged alphabetically by name 1961-1974 (Box-folder 4:12)
  - Campus revolution 1968 (Box-folder 4:13)
  - Carr's Hill - Architectural blueprints for additions and renovation 1959 (Oversize OS)
  - "Carr's Hill of the University of Virginia An Historical Sketch" n.d. (Box-folder 4:14)
  - Central Intelligence Agency - Commission on CIA Activities within the United States (Rockefeller Commission) 1975-1979 (Box-folder 5:1)
  - Certificates of Membership 1982 (Oversize OS)
    on the Governor's Task Force on Science and Technology and the Colgate Whitehead Darden, Jr. Memorial Committee given to Edgar Shannon
  - Colonial Williamsburg Foundation 1976-1988 (Box-folder 5:2)
  - Crispell, John 1968 (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Darlington School, Rome, Georgia 1933-1935 (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Duke University 1941-1946 (Box-folder 5:5)
  - Family Papers - certified records 1934-1945 (Box-folder 5:6)
  - Family Papers - Financial and Legal 1902-1917 (Box-folder 5:7)
  - Family Papers - Genealogy - Bragg, Cameron, and Finley Families 1932, n.d. (Box-folder 5:8)
  - Family Papers - Genealogy - Duncan Family n.d. (Box-folder 5:9)
  - Family Papers - Genealogy - Duncan Family n.d. (Box-folder 5:10)
  - Family Papers - Genealogy - Duncan Family Chart n.d. (Oversize OS)
  - Family Papers - Genealogy - McKean, Muse, Pendleton, and Reed Families 1904-1945, n.d. (Box-folder 5:11)
  - Family Papers - Genealogy - Rochester, Shannon, Thrift, and Waller Families n.d. (Box-folder 5:12)
  - Family Papers - Genealogy - Sanford-Lyne Families 1932-1951 (Box-folder 5:13)
  - Family Papers - Genealogy - Street Family n.d. (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Family Papers - Genealogy - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1932-1941 (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Family Papers - Genealogy - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1942-1954 (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Family Papers - Genealogy - Miscellaneous Notes and Correspondence 1934-1954 (Box-folder 6:4)
  - Family Papers - Genealogy - Miscellaneous Notes and Correspondence n.d. (Box-folder 6:5)
  - Family Papers - Writings by Isaac W. Duncan 1900-1905 (Box-folder 6:6)
  - Founder's Day - Press release for speech given by Adlai Stevenson 1960 Apr. 12 (Box-folder 6:7)
  - Harvard University 1909-1956, n.d. (Box-folder 6:8)
  - Honors and Awards 1931-1996 (Box-folder 6:9)
  - Mary Johnston - "Virginiana" 1931 (Box-folder 6:10)
  - Life Executive Space Tour 1964 (Box-folder 6:11)
  - Life Executive Space Tour - Journal 1964 (Box-folder 7:1)
  - Life Executive Space Tour - Michoud Operations Special Report 1964 Dec. 3 (Box-folder 7:2)
  - Life Executive Space Tour - Photographs 1965 (Box-folder 7:3)
  - Letters of Alfred, Lord Tennyson - Reviews 1982-1984 (Box-folder 7:4)
  - Letters of Alfred, Lord Tennyson - Reviews 1987-1992 (Box-folder 7:5)
  - Miscellaneous 1947, 1957 (Box-folder 7:6)
  - News clippings - Cavalier Daily 1969-1970 (Box-folder 7:7)
  - News clippings - Daily Progress 1970-1973 (Box-folder 7:8)
  - News clippings - President Hereford 1973-1974 (Box-folder 7:9)
  - News clippings - Inauguration of Shannon as President of the University of Virginia 1959 (Box-folder 7:10)
  - News clippings - Miscellaneous 1912-1991 (Box-folder 7:11)
  - News clippings - Retirement as University president 1973-1974 (Box-folder 7:12)
  - News clippings - Retirement from University 1988 (Box-folder 7:13)
  - News clippings - Revolutionary Ideology 1969-1970 (Box-folder 8:1)
  - News clippings - Seven Days in May 1970 (Box-folder 8:2)
  - News clippings - Shannon 1969-1991 (Box-folder 8:3)
  - News clippings - Student strikes (United States) 1968-1971, n.d. (Box-folder 8:4)
  - News clippings - Student strikes (University of Virginia) 1970, 1971, 1980 (Box-folder 8:5)
  - News clippings - University of Virginia 1962-1992 (Box-folder 8:6)
  - Obituaries 1997 (Box-folder 8:7)
  - Passport and travel documents for Edgar F. Shannon, Sr. and family 1920-1926 (Box-folder 8:8)
  - Photographs ca. 1954-1996 (Box-folder 8:9)
  - Photographs 1955-1976, n.d. (Box-folder 8:10)
  - Photographs 1948-1949, n.d. (Oversize OS)
    of Edgar and Eleanor Shannon, Frank Hereford, Dumas Malone and others at the University of Virginia; and a picture of Edgar Shannon's second year class at Merton College, Oxford
  - Photographs 1972 (Box-folder 8:11)
    Housing and Urban Development grant signing at Monticello and the University of Virginia
  - Photographs - U.S. Navy ca. 1940-1970 (Box-folder 8:12)
  - Presbyterianism - Printed 1940-1957 (Box-folder 8:13)
  - Programs 1923-1949 (Box-folder 8:14)
  - Programs 1968-1993 (Box-folder 8:15)
  - Report to the University Community 1970 (Box-folder 9:1)
  - Retirement as University President 1973-1974 (Box-folder 9:2)
  - Rhodes scholarship and reunions 1946-1952, 1965 (Box-folder 9:3)
  - School Papers of Edgar Shannon, Jr. 1923-1942, n.d. (Box-folder 9:4)
  - School Papers of Edgar Shannon, Jr. n.d. (Box-folder 9:5)
  - School Papers of Edgar Shannon, Jr. n.d. (Box-folder 9:6)
  - School Papers of Edgar Shannon, Jr. n.d. (Box-folder 9:7)
  - School Papers of Edgar Shannon, Jr. n.d. (Box-folder 9:8)
  - School Papers of Edgar Shannon, Jr. n.d. (Box-folder 9:9)
  - Seven Days in May 1968-1970 (Box-folder 9:10)
  - Seven Days in May 1970 (Box-folder 10:1)
  - Shannon, Edgar Finlay, Sr. 1918-1937 (Box-folder 10:2)
  - Shannon, Eleanor Bosworth (wife) 1965-1974 (Box-folder 10:3)
  - Shannon, Eleanor Duncan (mother) 1916-1943 (Box-folder 10:4)
  - Speeches 1964-1975, 1991 (Box-folder 10:5)
  - Stamps and Money 1940's (Box-folder 10:6)
  - Alfred, Lord Tennyson - Printed articles about 1961, 1992 (Box-folder 10:7)
  - Travel - England 1962-1968 (Box-folder 10:8)
  - Travel - England 1968-1970 (Box-folder 10:9)
  - Travel - England for Rhodes reunion 1983 (Box-folder 10:10)
  - Travel - England for Rhodes reunion 1983 (Box-folder 10:11)
  - Travel - Germany 1964 (Box-folder 11:1)
  - Travel - Japan 1965 (Box-folder 11:2)
  - Travel - Sweden and Norway 1943-1955 (Box-folder 11:3)
  - U.S. Navy - Annual qualifications questionnaire 1961-1971 (Box-folder 11:4)
  - U.S. Navy - Brochures, literature, pamphlets 1945-1973 (Box-folder 11:5)
  - U.S. Navy - Financial 1965-1972 (Box-folder 11:6)
  - U.S. Navy - Forms and evaluations 1965-1971 (Box-folder 11:7)
  - U.S. Navy - Medical 1965-1971 (Box-folder 11:8)
  - U.S. Navy - Naval record summary by Francis L. Berkeley, Jr. 1959 (Box-folder 11:9)
  - U.S. Navy - News clippings 1971-1982 (Box-folder 11:10)
  - U.S. Navy - Notes, miscellaneous 1971, n.d. (Box-folder 11:11)
  - U.S. Navy - Orders and correspondence 1942-1944 May (Box-folder 11:12)
  - U.S. Navy - Orders and correspondence 1944 Sep.-1945 (Box-folder 11:13)
  - U.S. Navy - Orders and correspondence 1946, 1959-1965 (Box-folder 12:1)
  - U.S. Navy - Orders and correspondence 1966-1968 (Box-folder 12:2)
  - U.S. Navy - Orders and correspondence 1969-1970 Sep. (Box-folder 12:3)
  - U.S. Navy - Orders and correspondence 1970 Oct.-1972 (Box-folder 12:4)
  - U.S. Navy Organizational Chart) 1968 (Oversize OS)
  - University of Virginia - Association of American Universities Spring Meeting 1974 (Box-folder 12:5)
  - University of Virginia - Memos 1969 Aug. (Box-folder 12:6)
    from Peter Low to President Shannon concerning Legal Matters, including Black Student enrollment, Black studies, and Admissions; the right of hourly employees to strike; and Student Discipline, Demonstrations, and the Student Judiciary System
  - University of Virginia - names to remember, guest lists 1961-1978 (Box-folder 12:7)
  - Washington and Lee University 1936-1939 (Box-folder 12:8)
  - Washington and Lee University - Class of 1939 Reunion 1989 (Box-folder 12:9)
  - Washington and Lee University - Coeducation 1983-1984 Jan. (Box-folder 12:10)
  - Washington and Lee University - Coeducation 1984 Feb.-Mar. (Box-folder 12:11)
  - Washington and Lee University - Coeducation 1984 Apr. (Box-folder 12:12)
  - Washington and Lee University - Coeducation 1984 May (Box-folder 13:1)
  - Washington and Lee University - Coeducation 1984 Jun.-Oct. (Box-folder 13:2)
  - Washington and Lee University - Coeducation - Correspondence concerning (copies removed from a notebook) 1983 (Box-folder 13:3)
  - Washington and Lee University - Reports concerning Admissions and the Financial Implications of Enrollments 1984 (Box-folder 13:4)
  - Washington and Lee University - Report concerning Campus Life 1984 (Box-folder 13:5)
  - Writings by Edgar F. Shannon 1958-1981, n.d. (Box-folder 13:6)
  - Writings by Edgar F. Shannon - Speeches (12706-e) 1964-1966 (Box-folder 13:7)
  - Writings by Edgar F. Shannon - Speeches (12706-e) 1967-1968 (Box-folder 13:8)
- Series IV: Scrapbooks, Photograph Albums, Other Bound Volumes, and Memorabilia (Box 14-18)
  - Address book n.d. (Box-folder 14:1)
  - Calendar kept by Eleanor B. Shannon 1958 (Box-folder 14:2)
  - Calendar kept by Eleanor B. Shannon 1960 (Box-folder 14:3)
  - Calendar kept by Eleanor B. Shannon 1961 (Box-folder 14:4)
  - Calendar kept by Eleanor B. Shannon 1962 (Box-folder 14:5)
  - Calendar kept by Eleanor B. Shannon 1963 (Box-folder 14:6)
  - Calendar kept by Eleanor B. Shannon 1964 (Box-folder 14:7)
  - Calendar kept by Eleanor B. Shannon 1966 (Box-folder 14:8)
  - Calendar kept by Eleanor B. Shannon 1967 (Box-folder 14:9)
  - Calendar kept by Eleanor B. Shannon 1968 (Box-folder 14:10)
  - Calendar kept by Eleanor B. Shannon 1969 (Box-folder 14:11)
  - Calendar kept by Eleanor B. Shannon 1970 (Box-folder 14:12)
  - Calendar kept by Eleanor B. Shannon 1971 (Box-folder 14:13)
  - Calendar kept by Eleanor B. Shannon 1972 (Box-folder 14:14)
  - Century Outline for a Course in English Literature 1914-1938 (Box-folder 14:15)
    with Teaching notes written in the book
  - Diary - Eleanor Duncan Shannon 1926 (Box-folder 14:16)
  - Diploma, Bridgewater College 1971 (Box-folder 14:17)
  - Diploma, The Ohio State University 1981 (Box-folder 14:18)
  - Guestbook kept by the Shannons 1956-1960 (Box-folder 15:1)
  - Guestbook kept by the Shannons 1961 (Box-folder 15:2)
  - Guestbook kept by the Shannons 1961-1964 (Box-folder 15:3)
  - Guestbook kept by the Shannons 1964-1970 (Box-folder 15:4)
  - Guestbook kept by the Shannons 1971-1975 (Box-folder 15:5)
  - Guestbook kept by the Shannons 1975-1982 (Box-folder 15:6)
  - Guestbook kept by the Shannons 1982-1992 (Box-folder 15:7)
  - Guestbook kept by the Shannons n.d. (Box-folder 15:8)
  - Guestbook kept by the Shannons n.d. (Box-folder 15:9)
  - Guestbook kept by the Shannons n.d. (Box-folder 15:10)
  - Memorabilia - Atlantic Coast Conference Basketball Champion Plaque 1976 (Box-folder 16:1)
  - Memorabilia - Gavel presented to Shannon by the National Association of State Universities and Land-Grant Colleges 1983 (Box-folder 16:2)
  - Memorabilia - Medal from the Most Venerable Order of the Hospital of St. John of Jerusalem 1968 Aug. 25-29 (Box-folder 16:4)
  - Memorabilia - Virginia State Flag on a miniature flagpole and a [Pointing?] Stick n.d. (Oversize OS)
  - Memorabilia - Wings pin n.d. (Box-folder 16:5)
  - Memorabilia - Women's Athletics Recognition "Medal" for Shannon 1973 (Box-folder 16:6)
  - Notebook - Biology 1937 (Box-folder 16:7)
  - Oxford University Engravings 1837, 1842 (Box-folder 16:8)
  - Photograph Album 1961 (Box-folder 16:9)
    Virginia Military Institute and the Inauguration of Superintendent George Richard Edwin Shell
  - Photograph album 1959 (Box-folder 17:1)
    Inauguration of Edgar F. Shannon as President of the University of Virginia
  - Photograph album ca. 1961-1970 (Box-folder 17:2)
    University of Virginia
  - Photograph album 1964 (Box-folder 17:3)
    U.S. Naval Academy Visit of Edgar F. Shannon as a Member of the 1964 Board of Visitors
  - Photograph album 1995-1996 (Box-folder 17:4)
    Dedication of Shannon Center
  - Scrapbook - Mississippi River Flood 1937 (Box-folder 17:5)
  - Scrapbook - Shannon's Inauguration 1959 (Box-folder 17:6)
  - Scrapbook - Shannon's Inauguration 1959-1960 (Box-folder 17:7)
  - Scrapbook - Shannon at the University of Virginia 1959-1980 (Box-folder 18:1)
  - Scrapbook - Shannon at the University of Virginia 1974-1982 (Box-folder 18:2)
  - Scrapbook - Shannon at the University of Virginia 1978-1995 (Box-folder 18:3)